A Guide to the Letters of Julien Green 1927-1939
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Letters of Julien Green
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10792
This collection consists of 12 letters.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The letters were given to the library by Peter Hoy of Merton College, Oxford University, on September 14, 1988.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of Julien Green, a Parisian novelist of American parentage, is comprised of 12 autograph letters signed spanning 1927-1939 possibly to [Jacques Patin, an editor at Le Figaro] regarding publication of Green's personal journals in excerpts in the Paris newspaper Le Figaro and in book form. (The journals were ultimately published in 1972 as Journal: 1926-1972, 9 vols., and partially translated in 1939 as Personal Record 1928-1939 and in 1962 as Diary 1928-1957.) All the letters are in French.
Green is initially resistant to the project: ".. .I have given much thought to your request, which is a great honor to me, but I don't believe, unfortunately, that I'm able to send you a paper that would satisfy both of us. I could, doubtless, write a page or two which we could call a summary, but neither you nor I would be happy with it.. ." (undated letter). But he soon complies: "I have been in bad health and preoccupied lately and haven't sent you anything, but I am in the process of finishing an article that you are going to receive from here in two or three days.. .[I] am going to publish my journal, or a part of my journal, towards the end of May... I will try to choose excerpts in a way of forming a homogenous whole.. ." (undated letter).
Later letters include discussions of Green's growing enthusiasm for the project (22 May 1927 and 27 June 192[7?]); the importance of the printers following the corrected proofs carefully (".. .It's important that the words to omit completely disappear.. .I'm thinking in particular of the first page.. ."; undated letter); and the publication of excerpts in Le Figaro (3 May 1938, 29 March 1939).
Contents List
- Julien Green to Jacques Patin 1927 May 22
  Green writes enthusiastically about something the editor has left for him to read and says he owes to the editor his ability to write on the subject of his book; with envelope.
- Julien Green to [Jacques Patin?] [1927 June 27
- Julien Green to [Jacques Patin?] 1938 May 3
  Discusses the appropriate payment for publication of excerpts from the journals; "It is impossible, in short, to accept less than 100 francs for an installment.. ."
- Julien Green to [Jacques Patin?] 1938 May 4
  Letter accompanying corrected proofs, asking that the accuracy of the correctioins be checked
- Julien Green to [Jacques Patin?] 1938 Oct. 13
- Julien Green to [Jacques Patin?] 1939 Mar. 29
  ["Here is the year 1938 of my journal. I hope that it will interest you and that you could excerpt some of it to fill a few columns in Le Figaro.. ."
- Julien Green to [Jacques Patin?] n.d.
  ".. .I have given much thought to your request, which is a great honor to me, but I don't believe, unfortunately, that I'm able to send you a paper which would satisfy both of us. I could, doubtless, write a page or two that we could call a summary, but you wouldn't be very happy -- nor I.. ."
- Julien Green to [Jacques Patin?] n.d.
  "You have asked me for a chronicle. Here is one that, I hope, you can use.. ."
- Julien Green to [Jacques Patin?] n.d.
  "I have been rather ill and preoccupied lately and haven't sent you anything, but I am in the process of finishing an article that you are going to receive in two or three days. I am going to publish.. .a part of my journal towards the end of May.. .I will try to choose excerpts in a way of forming a homogenous whole.. ."
- Julien Green to [Jacques Patin?] n.d.
  Expresses concerns about accuracy of proofreading; writes "The word 'millionaire' was replaced by 'grand seigneur,' but is it thus throughout?.. ."
- Julien Green to [Jacques Patin?] n.d.
  expresses gratitude for the editor's part in publishing excerpts of Green's journal in Le Figaro